[Music]
so
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the eleventy first episode of
the ask a budget show
the the ask a budget show is now 11
episodes old 111 episodes old and
and we just keep going as always so uh
let me see who all is there with us uh
vitamin protein vault gaming samira das
sketch
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you great to be again
back with you all
so
today we're doing history geopolitics
current affairs all those things so
shall we get into it so as always i've
picked a bunch of questions and
hopefully if there is time at the end we
will take a few questions from the live
chat at the end so let's get right into
it my hobbits
what's question number one question
number one is by rahul gupta what's your
take on india
reopening its embassy in afghanistan
what might be india's intentions
so uh
we are re-normalizing our relationship
with afghanistan i mean uh
when did the taliban take over happen i
think it happened in august 2021 which
is less than a year ago and at that time
i i said
that very soon afghanistan and india
will again be on the same page the
taliban do not hate india contrary to
whatever the media says and all that the
taliban have absolutely no antipathy
towards india
and they prefer india towards to
pakistan they would prefer to be on the
side of india and cooperate with india
then to cooperate with pakistan and that
is something we're going to see over the
long period of over the long run
so 10 it's been 10 or so months which is
still a very short period of time in the
context of history and geopolitics it's
like an eye blink of a time that's all
it is and yet we are seeing the
reopening of the indian embassy in
afghanistan we sent a military plane
with our officials and uh
diplomats and personnel and we are
reopening it so
so even when kabul was being taken over
by the taliban last year in august
then two
they ensured very clearly they made sure
that all indians are evacuated safely
there are no issues whether it is indian
diplomats or officials or civilians
everybody was allowed to depart safely
and even some afghans were allowed to
get on the indian plains
the ones that the indian government
wanted to take take out of afghanistan
but the taliban cooperated even at that
time but there was a period of chaos the
period of
uncertainty in the country now the
taliban are reasonably uh
well in charge they are in control of
the country more or less all the various
issues are
well
are more or less in the control of
course
i don't want to go into the internal
matters of how they are running the
country what policies they are adopting
that's their business
as long as they don't interfere in my
business i will not interfere in their
business so the taliban want to
re-establish proper
diplomatic and other relationships with
india india is sending wheat and other
things to the country
so that's where we are
in the long run india and afghanistan
whatever government is there in
afghanistan india and afghanistan have
shared interests
and shared concerns and the shared
concern we know what it is it is
pakistan the afghans whether it is the
taliban or anybody else views pakistan
as the enemy they have the afghans have
a big territorial dispute with the
pakistanis
they seek their territory back from
pakistan so that's something that's not
going anywhere that issue
and the pakistanis everyone knows wants
to they want to use afghanistan as their
strategic backyard they would like to
destroy afghanistan and use the people
of afghanistan as cannon fodder in
a hoped for eventual war with india
that's what the pakistanis want and
obviously that is going to be at the
detriment of the afghan nation and
afghan people
so even if the taliban is in power and
people say that it's a it's a pakistani
creation and still you see that the
taliban wants to have good relations
with india so that is where we are we
are reopening our embassy uh i am i
don't know what what discussions have
happened obviously there have been
discussions happening between the indian
government and the taliban yeah we are
not privy to those discussions we don't
know what has been discussed as
obviously we should not know what is
discussed certain things are not
supposed to be in the public sphere in
the public domain so
there have been discussions going on and
the result of these discussions is that
we are reopening our embassy there the
taliban has been requesting india for
quite some time to reopen its embassies
and all that and they have assured they
will provide adequate security and
obviously we will send our own security
personnel to guard and defend our
embassy in case of any eventualities so
all of that must have been ironed out by
now all the terms and we are back in
afghanistan great job and good good
development and we just need to keep
going forward and strengthen our
relationship with
afghanistan again
so good development that's my take on
this
next question ashutosh says don't you
think that the russia ukraine war has
shown us
how incompetent the russian defense
forces are as they are losing on every
front as shown by the media
which media are you consuming sir
which media
the media that we
tend to consume in india is the
english-speaking media now who controls
the english-speaking media it's the west
now on what side is the west they are
anti-russia pro-ukraine so obviously
they will show russia as being
incompetent and
and
losing everything but take a look at
what's on the map i will i'm not going
to show the map today i mean the exact
situation here's the deal here is the
situation on the ground today
russia
has captured
approximately one-fourth
of ukrainian territory
the amount of territory ukraine had
before february 24 2022
out of that territory at least one
fourth is now in russia under russian
control
that is a territory larger than the size
of bangladesh or nepal do you think that
is incompetence
they have been portraying the russian
advance as as like the russia see we
don't know what the russian intentions
were or are right
they will not
telegraph their intentions before they
start the war or even while fighting the
war
in warfare everything is about deception
you want the enemy to be confused you
want the adversary to not know what your
true intentions are
like in chess as in war it's all about
deception
so maybe the russians only wanted
certain territories maybe the the
dunbar's region the eastern region of
ukraine which is uh russian speaking
mostly majority and the coastal regions
in the black sea uh the ports of
this side et cetera perhaps this is
still probably not under control maybe
they will take it under control i mean
so that's what it could be maybe they
don't want to take over the entirety of
ukraine but they want to ensure that
ukraine can never rise again as a threat
against russia and as a puppet of the of
the west right
so that may have been the intention
they have done
a good job as if that was the intention
that's that's what they've already
achieved they've taken over a quarter of
the entire country
they're consolidating their their uh
their positions there they are fully in
control of one-fourth of the earthquake
territories of ukraine and
let's see how it goes i don't see
incompetence the western media will only
show a certain image and if you want to
consume that wholesale well good luck to
you but in i mean even the indian media
you will see various journalists who
have been and who had been embedded with
ukrainian forces i mean if you want to
to to give a balanced picture of a
conflict to your people to your country
shouldn't you also have a few reporters
embedded on the other side but no they
only showed a one-sided picture so
that's where we are the map the
positions on the ground are very clear
russia has taken over a quarter of the
country i don't see that as in the
incompetence
of course there have been losses on both
sides
it's clear that the ukrainians have lost
more their armed forces are decimated
they are they're completely dependent on
supplies coming in from nato from the
west and still they're not able to
retake the territory and they're they're
gradually
losing more if the russians so desire
i don't see that as incompetence of
course the russians haven't done an
outstanding job they have also suffered
casualties and losses
and for that that's why you need to
understand history you cannot understand
current affairs or geopolitics unless
you have a good grasp on about history
and when it comes to the russia ukraine
conflict that's going going on right now
you need to look at the russia the
history of russia the past
300 years
here's the deal
every time russia has gone into a
conflict whether it is in the 19th
century whether it is with the turks
whether it is during world war 1 or
world war ii or whatever initially they
have always suffered catastrophic losses
always that's always been the pattern in
russia in in wars involving russia or
the ussr initially they always suffer
disastrous losses and then they get back
so that's where we are in this case the
russians have not suffered disastrous
losses as such but
they would have suffered some losses
they lost one of their major battleships
yeah
and
maybe some some soldiers and personnel
as well but overall they're in control
so i don't see this as incompetence i
don't see the russians have as having
suffered setbacks they have not lost
territory they've gained a substantial
amount of territory they're holding on
to it and the west is not able to do
anything about it neither is ukraine
so that's where we are and that's what
the situation is so i would encourage
you
to look at a 360 degree perspective
don't only consume english speaking
media look at the french media try and
translate that there are translation
tools available look at what the germans
are saying but look at what the russians
are saying their media look at what the
chinese are saying i know it's all
everything is propaganda russian news is
propaganda chinese uses propaganda
western news is major major propaganda
but look at everything from a holistic
360 degree perspective and then you will
get a better idea of what's really
happening
and the best way to know what's
happening in the contract is to look at
the situation on a map who's controlling
what and that tells you clearly there is
no incompetence on the russian side
they've at once significantly taken a
quarter of the country so that's where
we are and that's what i have to say
about this sir all the best
akash says why is the russian federation
sidelined as an eternal enemy by the
entire western world in spite of them
belonging to the same ethnicity and
religion they even fought on the same
side in the world wars now why is there
such an enmity or rather a hatred
amongst the
ordinary folks of these european
countries towards russia
and weren't they better off being allies
of russia considering their own national
interests instead of facing a constant
threat from it
so to understand this situation we have
to again look at history the past
thousand years of history
the past thousand years of history if
you look at it from a big picture
perspective it's
a history of constant tribal warfare in
europe ethnic strife
whether it's the balkan regions whether
it's the austro-hungarian region uh
romania wallachia the ottoman empire was
involved for a very long period of time
uh
the saxons the the german principle it
is the russian empire which was for some
time for a significant amount of time
under the russia under the mongol yoke
the franks the merovingians the the
english the spaniards the portuguese
it's a constant story of ethnic strife
ethnic hatred i did not even speak about
the italians
and so on
and historically there's been a major
force one major force in europe which is
the roman catholic church the vatican
right and they have typically uh lorded
over europe now the thing is this
the russians are not quite the same
ethnicity as the as the rest of europe
uh europe western europe sees russia as
an eastern
as an eastern entity it the western
europe sees russia as part of the east
ethnically culturally etc even the
russian religion the russian orthodox
christianity is very different from the
christianity that's practiced in other
parts of europe it's way more
traditional there are lots of elements
of paganism in that
yeah
below the surface
so that's how it is and
even from an ethnic perspective
uh the russians have a lot of
what would you call it
mongol blood
or turkic blood lots of them yeah so
it's a russia has been a country that's
always expanded eastwards and they've
heard a lot of dealings in siberia and
eastern asia eastern eurasia and they
have intermingled with lots of peoples
nomadic peoples etc the so-called tatars
and so on who lived in these regions and
over the centuries these peoples have
intermingled lots of russians consider
themselves to be tatars even they don't
look even if they don't look eastern
asian at all yeah
uh i can think of what was that
there were two siblings tennis players a
male and a female
who were both the grand slam champions i
forget their names but
yeah they are tatars and lots of other
people so russia is a melting pot of
east and west it's more of east than
west right
so uh ethnically they are
the ethnicity is different the europeans
consider russians to be part of the east
religion is also different it's a very
very orthodox and conservative form of
christianity with pagan elements
and if you look at the various conflicts
that have happened in europe russia has
always has always been kind of an
outsider
and as russia expanded in the 19th
century became more powerful and there
were periods of expansion during the
times of catherine the great peter the
great ivan the terrible and so on so
russia has always been seen as a threat
an outside threat to europe it's always
been that way even in the world wars
uh
russia was
russia bled a lot for let's go to the
second world war
the
russians and the nazis had a brief
agreement
the molotov riben trump pact which
happened in 1939 or something like that
yeah it held for a couple of years
and at that time russia was
technically on the side of the nazis on
the side of hitler and the rest of
europe saw russia as as well the enemy
and it's only when hitler
launched his disastrous operation
barbarossa that russia became part of
the allies and that was a disaster
it was almost a success
the nazis came to the gates of moscow
but eventually they were
they were wiped out by the red army
at the expense of millions of lives and
oceans of blood so that's how it was
so europe we see it as a very civilized
stable place it's not the case the first
world war in the second world war were
essentially the same conflict the 30
30-35-year conflict
and i call it the european tribal war
that's what it is europe has always been
a place of ethnic hatreds old vendettas
look at the balkans look at the history
of the how the french and the germans
and the italians the spanish the british
they have always fought each other lots
of petty jealousies and rivalries all
vying for the same piece of the pie even
in the era of colonialism they were
fighting each other for pieces of other
pies and that's how it is
so overall if you study history you will
see that the europeans especially the
western europeans have always seen
russia as an outsider as an eastern
power as a backward power they've always
considered russia to be backward and
eastern east and backward is
more or less the same thing in the minds
of the europeans so that's how it is
and even when you look at uh
the pronouncements and and the overall
um
statements of dr s joshua from from a
geopolitical perspective today it's
clear that he does not view
russia as part of the west
russia is part of the east
and the russians too
are way closer to india than they are to
any part any part of western europe and
so on even today or in the 20th century
so there's it's always been that way
and
yeah so that's the situation overall
and there are ethnic
conflicts and hatreds europe is full of
these ethnic hatreds
it's all that's how it is so that's what
i can explain in brief i would encourage
you all
to study
history because that makes things more
clear
there's a lot to unpack you can have a
one year
uh two two-semester course
that will touch upon these things in in
a little in a little bit of depth and
still it won't be enough so that's how
big this thing is but overall europe
sees russia as an outside force as an
eastern force as a backward country and
something to be subdued and something to
be scared of rather than something to be
embraced that's how it has always been
always
ryo says
share your knowledge about the king of
wallachia vlad the impaler the way he
slaughtered the ottoman turks and
impaled them alive in a wooden stake and
the way he ruthlessly and ferociously
defended europe from the ottoman turks
and on the contrary
why did indian kings have navy
naive and forgiving approach while
dealing with all invaders all right
yes we have never spoken about vlad the
impeller a very interesting and
significant figure figure in
the europe of the middle ages vlad the
impeller
the impaler what a name what a sobriquet
he had got so this uh person was a
warlord you could call him a king or a
ruler
in wallachia which is uh
in southern romania also let's take a
look at look at the map where's the map
as you all know i am a very big fan of
the map so let's go to the map i hope i
have it open somewhere so where is this
part of the world it's obviously in
europe
so let's bring europe to the forefront
center of the screen here
so this is romania and wallachia is
somewhere here
in the eastern
or so part of romania maybe towards the
south of romania roughly roughly this
region roughly this part of the world
all right
you can look it up yourselves in greater
detail
if uh yeah so it's in romania
and in roughly this part of the world
so vlad the impeller was a warlord a
voivode
of this place in the 15th century
between the 1430s and the 1470s for the
1480s that's that's his
uh that's where his lifetime occurred
right
so he ruled over this region two or
three times the first time was around
the 14 late 1440s then in the mid 1450s
and 1460s and again for a while in the
1470s right so it was a turbulent
tumultuous life uh he was the son of one
of the warlords his father was also
called vlad vlad the first vlad ii
something like that and as a child
vlad the impaler
and his brother i forget the name these
two kids were taken hostage by the
ottoman empire in order to make their
father behave
so at that time the ottoman empire was a
big deal very big deal one of the major
maybe the major power in europe and it
was well
an occupying invasive power they had
taken over the byzantine empire
yeah
they had taken over the territory of the
byzantine empire uh
anatolia which was historically part of
greece in the eastern roman empire and
parts of europe so let's once again go
to the map
so the present-day turkey
and the present-day balkan regions parts
of romania
and the
extent and influence of the ottoman
empire was vast at the time
okay
so that's how it was that's uh that was
the situation at the time
i hope the the
my image is clear i hope it's clear
if it is not let me know and i will try
and fix it
i think it's clear i hope yeah
right so so this was a situation so the
ottoman empire was a major power in this
region they were a brutal
occupying power and all these various uh
ethnicities and national nationalities
in europe eastern europe etc were
attempting to free themselves from this
horrific terrifying brutal
barbaric
yoke of the turks right
so one of these freedom fighters was
this was this person vlad the impaler so
like i said he was hostage for a while
he and his brother in the court of the
ottomans
uh the ottoman sultan at the time was
there were two sultans who
uh were
in power during the lifetime of vladimir
the first one was murad the second and
the second one was muhammad ii i think
he is also known as
he is a very significant ottoman king
right muhammad ii
so uh eventually what happens is that
this guy vlad goes back to his his
country his territory he becomes the
vote or the war lord or the ruler of the
place and he wages a conflict he wages a
war against the ottomans against the
turks
and sometime in the 19 in the 1460s
the turks tried to invade his territory
he fights back he takes the fight to
ottoman territory
he fights a battle against an army made
up of turks and bulgarians
and he massacres i mean he defeats this
army there are more than 20 30 40 000
casualties i don't remember the exact
number
and what he does is frightful
he what he does
is all these uh
dead soldiers and those who were
captured he impales them
on wooden stakes in the ground you take
a stake you put it in the ground yeah
a spear point kind of thing you place it
in the ground standing up and then you
impale a human body on top of it
frightful
it was one of the
ways of torturing and executing people
very painful very horrible obviously
very brutal but
vlad realized that this is the only
language that turks understand
yeah so what he did was he impaled
i don't know how many people tens of
thousands maybe 20 30 40 000 turkish and
bulgarian soldiers
in one location it's like a forest of
impaled corpses so when the ottomans
came again that way they encountered
this
incredibly frightening site
20 30 000 of maybe 40 000 of their own
troops impaled on
on on stakes in the ground an entire
forest
of such impaled corpses
and the ottoman sultan muhammad ii was
extraordinarily
impressed
he said that a a man a ruler who can do
such great
deeds
should not be defeated and should should
be treasured that sort of thing so like
i said
vlad spoke the vlad knew which language
the turks spoke and he spoke to them in
their language and eventually it was a
tumultuous life he he was defeated a
couple of times he went out of power
then he came back to power he even
fought the saxons the germans and so on
and over time what happened is that
these stories about him
began to proliferate
and that's how he got the title of vlad
the impaler
and lots of stories of extreme cruelty
uh started spreading because
mainly through the saxons the germans
because he was their enemy too and when
somebody is your enemy you typically try
to indulge in propaganda warfare and try
to portray that person as a very
barbaric and cruel and evil person so
that's how these stories proliferated
and so that's that's the thing about
vlad the impeller that in brief is his
life he i think he died in the 1470s
yeah at the end of a very eventful life
now the thing is this
he he belonged to a lineage called the
house of the dragon i think that's what
it was called the house of the dragon
and the word for dragon in the romanian
language is draculi
so he was called
dracula
vlad the dragon
and the the
the irish writer the british writer
bram stoker
took inspiration from this region
romania the carpathian region where
there are these folk tales of of
nosferatu the vampire and he tied that
with the
name of this lineage draculia and he
created this this character of dracula
right the very famous vampire story
dracula
so that was inspired by the story of
vlad draculia
vlad the dragon
so that in brief
is the story
of vlad the impaler he was ruthless he
defended his country he defended europe
by by extension from the turks
and
he was one of them he is considered a
national hero in romania i believe
so he understood
what language the turks
spoke and he spoke to them in their
language the language of brutality and
barbarity and maybe indian kings were a
little forgiving yeah
we indians are way too civilized when
when you deal with barbarians you deal
with them in their language in their
terms i think we kind of uh
did not quite get it
so yeah that's one deficiency we our
rulers overall typically have had not
all but most of them so that's yeah
that's just facts
okay saurabh says who was zoroaster
what's his history and who is ahura
mazda the god of zoroaster and what was
the culture of persia before him
so we don't quite know when this person
zoroaster lived
uh he most likely lived about three
thousand or so years ago roughly give or
take yeah so who was this this person
his name was zarathustra
right zarath ustra so in sanskrit that
the word ustra or ustra means kamal
and the word zarat
most likely means either yellow or old
so zarath
either means yellow camel or old camel
yeah in sanskrit
and sanskrit was
the the language of ancient persia the
old persian language was like an upper
branch
dialect of sanskrit that's how it was so
zarathustra means either yellow camel or
old camel or maybe golden camel or
something like that yeah that's what it
means clearly ushr means camel
so that's who he was and now he came up
with this
religion he said the god the great god
ahura
i don't know he came to me in my dream
of what i don't know what the exact
foundational myth is but he was the
first prophet in the first originator of
a revealed religion which is which is
now called zoroastrianism the the the
and that was adopted by the
persian empire the achaemenid empire the
haksha manish empire and this uh
cult this religion zoroastrianism became
the state religion of persia
so that's what it is we don't know
exactly when he lived it's kind of lost
in the midst of history
it is believed that he was born in
bahalik in bulk which is present day
afghanistan which is presently in
afghanistan currently i think that's
where he was born that spirit he is
believed to have been born
right
and for and somehow he was able to
propagate his his
belief system which is an inversion
the zoroastrian zoroastrian belief
system is essentially an inversion of
the vedic religion
so the devas in in in vedic traditions
the devas are have a positive
connotation and the asuras
have a kind of slightly negative
connotation not all asuras are bad but
asuras are kind of on the opposing side
of the devas so in the the
zoroastrian system the devas become the
evil guys and the ahuras asuras
become the good guys that's how it is
and the greatest of the ahuras or asuras
is
the great god and that's how it is but
what people don't realize is that
zoroastrianism is not a monotheistic
belief system there's a multitude of
gods and divinities and all that right
so it is just as polytheistic as their
ancestral religion was vedic hinduism so
what was the culture of persia before
zoroastrianism obviously it was hinduism
vedic vedic hinduism what we call
hinduism now it was the vedic culture
traditions and if you want to call it
religion religion
so before zoroaster before zarathustra
the culture of persia was the same as
the culture of india the persians are
descendants of an
ancient indian clan that was defeated
in a great vedic era battle the battle
of the 10 to 15 or 20 kings it was more
than 10 and one of these defeated clans
was the parshwa clan the the pursue or
the parshwa clan right and they went
westwards they escaped all the all of
the clans that were defeated were
expelled out of india they had to escape
in order to survive
it was the bharatas
under the great king sudas who won
this conflict
and because of that india is now known
as bharat
so that's ins that's in briefs of the
persians are the descendants of the
parshwa clan of the rigvedic people they
were the descendants of indians and it's
even today you see similarities in
language culture and so on
now the culture is obviously a shia
mostly shia islam yeah
but there are strata of culture that lie
below that and you can see some
some
traces of their original culture deep
deep below
yeah so that's what it is
kieran says should billionaires exist
jeff bezos spent 5.5 billion on a
10-minute space trip elon musk said
spent 47 billion dollars on an
underground tunnel system to solve
traffic the tunnels ended up being
exclusive to tesla cars
that much money could have been spent on
improving public transport most
billionaires spend money in a selfish
manner should there be an upper cap on
wealth well
his highness the great bernie sanders
wants billionaires to be abolished and
he wants them to be taxed and he says
there should be no billionaires
see if you have billionaires it's
because
the system
allows billionaires to to rise
uh
the us is an out and out capitalist
country
the system is fully capitalistic right
nowadays there is more of a pro
marxist kind of uh
reconfiguration the society is becoming
more and more pro-left that's a
different story but historically the u.s
has been a capitalist society and there
is no cap on how wealthy you can become
in that and that's why you have this
massive
wealth inequality in the u.s
the top two percent of the the
wealth is owned by
no 80 of the wealth is owned by two
percent of the people or something like
that you know roughly like that massive
massive wealth and income disparities
and people who are below the poverty
line or near the poverty line are forced
to work two three jobs
a day 14 15 16 hours a day in order to
just bring a little bit of food to the
table for the families that's the kind
of incredibly inequal unequal system it
is
in the u.s if you are wealthy it's a
wonderful place to live in you have the
whole world is open to you but if you're
not wealthy it's it's it's terrible
so the question is is bill should
billionaires exist listen i have nothing
against billionaires
uh
the system encourages competition the
system encourages innovation
and people who do this will accrue the
rewards of that
you innovate
you compete well
and you come out on top you're gonna be
very wealthy that's how it is now i
think the billionaires are taxed very
less and all that so there are pros and
cons to this thing
i don't think we should abolish
billionaires
maybe billionaires see once you have
earned a certain amount of wealth it's
yours and you can do whatever you want
with it right you could donate it to
charity like some people pretend to do
charities that have certain purposes
yeah or you could just splurge it all or
whatever
so it's up to them i say i i would i
would say i would definitely want
billionaires and wealthy people to live
responsible lives and contribute to
society i mean you become wealthy
when you contribute something to society
you don't become wealthy by stealing
wealth
these people in a capitalistic system
you have to solve the problems that
society is facing you have to offer
value to society in exchange you acquire
wealth that's how it works and i think
that's a fair trade
obviously you can't have
a capitalist system in which the only
objective is quarter upon quarter profit
and a never-ending expansion at the
expense of the resources and the
environment environment of our planet
so that's what we have in the west and
that's why the world the environment is
in such trouble today because of the
extremely
irresponsible
way in which these corporations expand i
mean
consider a television set
these days we have these flat screen tvs
these tvs they cost a lot of money to
make they it takes a lot of resources in
the
various kinds of rare earths and various
metals and various things that you have
to extract out of the earth's surface
yeah to manufacture one tv these tvs
will cost you i don't know whatever it
costs
fifty thousand rupees hundred thousand
rupees whatever depending on the size
configuration and so on these flat
screen tvs typically last two or three
years and then the screen goes blank and
you dump it in the trash and buy a new
one these companies they make sure these
tvs don't last long
yeah so that you have to keep buying new
television sets every couple of years
and all of it's it's a perfectly good
machine but the screen goes blank and
you have to replace it that's what
happens isn't that an incredibly
irresponsible
waste of resources
that's what's destroying the planet
whether it's tvs whether it is cell
phones they want you to keep buying new
devices every couple of years or every
year ideally and that is what's
destroying the planet and many of these
billionaires they become billionaires by
indulging in such practices and that's
not frowned upon and
at the end of the day they blame india
and china for pollution
so the overall system needs to be looked
at and it needs to be uh
reformed on an urgent basis uh
but i would not blame elon musk or jeff
bezos alone solely for this elon musk is
not
so elon musk hasn't been indulging in
such practices his his companies are not
overall that bad
for the environment he is this solar
company
which is reasonably good which is
actually trying to solve a certain
problem that we should not extract uh we
should not use fossil fuels for for uh
electricity we should use solar power
it's a good thing the tesla company it's
all about
electric vehicles that doesn't quite
solve the problem because you can
generate electricity by burning coal for
instance and the lithium-ion batteries
they use are not quite good for the
environment so there are problems
everywhere but
it needs to be looked at judiciously we
should not straight away abolish
billionaires and if that happens and
people will not have any incentive to
work hard and innovate and make the
world a better place so there have to be
there's there's given this give and take
this pros and cons
uh overall capitalism is not completely
bad but it has to be done responsibly
not at the expense of the planet and not
the at the expense of other countries
so
that's how it is but i don't see these
problems being solved anytime soon so
that's where we are so i would say that
it's the western capitalistic system
which is the root cause of all of this
the good as well as the bad
lakshya says i recently saw a video in
which a remova
wedding was being performed so what is
the indigenous religion of lithuania
the pre-christian religion and culture
of lithuania yeah where is lithuania
let's take a look at the map just in
case you're not aware
lithuania
is
over here
yeah
western europe north western europe
the baltic sea latvia lithuania estonia
the three baltic nations that were once
part of the ussr and here you have
kaliningrad which is a different story
so that's lithuania
uh
so you lecture saw a video in which a
remover wedding was being performed in
accordance with vedic rituals
and i expect there would have been a
vedic priest
yeah
who would be perform an indian vedic
priest who would perform who would
officiate over this ritual
so the question is can we encourage
europe to rediscover and embrace its
pre-christian cultures
good question so there is a certain
underground movement in europe
which
whose objective is to rediscover
uh the pre-christian traditions
and embrace those traditions and bring
them again to the forefront so you have
the remova movement in
lithuania latvia also i suppose you have
something called there is a nordic
revivalism also
there is a religion called asatru or
something which kind of is
is a 21st century
embrace
of the nordic religion in which you had
this the gods like thor odin and so
freyja and so on so forth which is well
the the nordic viking pantheon was
was a reflection of the old vedic
pantheon the entirety of europe had the
same culture overall with different
local manifestations and different names
of the gods but overall it was the same
even in the slavic regions
there is a movement to kind of
rediscover the old slavic heritage
which is again a continuation of the
ancient vedic heritage yeah so that's
what's happening at a certain level in
europe it's still very much underground
it's still very much in a small minority
but these movements are being are
visible in various parts of europe
so the question is can we encourage
europe to rediscover and embrace its
pre-christian cultures see that will
happen only
see if you look at india today everybody
is trying to copy and ape the west
look at the teenagers of today look at
the kids look at gen z zoomers
what are they doing they're trying to
copy the west they're trying to ape the
west why is it
because the west is so dominant because
the west is cool
yeah the west has very positive and
powerful connotations
people
want to be cool
people want to copy those who are
powerful
in ancient europe everybody wanted to be
roman everybody wanted to copy roman
styles of
architecture sculpture
the way of life and all that
so whichever is the dominant culture
overall
statistically most people want to copy
that ape that that's what happens so if
we want europe to rediscover and embrace
its pre-christian cultures
we in india our nation
needs to rise as a civilization and
become one of the dominant powers in the
world then
the pre-christian traditions will be
cool again
so for this
cultural shift to happen india has to
rise again
india has to reclaim
its historical pre-eminent role in in
the world
economically militarily and culturally
india is currently defined as a so as a
secular socialist nation state
india has to
reclaim its position
as a civilization as a civilization
state right now we are not there
so when that happens
the pre-christian cultures of europe
will become cool again
right now they're not cool they're just
a small minority an underground movement
so
all of you together
need to
come together and make india rise again
once that happens
this cultural change will happen
sparker kaiser says i started i just
started reading about the white hounds
the hephthalites why did the
hephthalites destroyed takshashila
taxila what's taxila it's takshashila
why did these people the heptalites the
white hounds the shwetahunas destroy
takshashila university if they
assimilated in indian culture
assuming that they did it while invading
why didn't they rebuild it to repay the
destruction they had done if they
respected indian culture some stories
had hindu versus buddhism angle can you
please clarify this all right
okay so where is
is in western india now it's in pakistan
somewhere in
present-day pakistani punjab let's take
a look
where is dr sheila and it's gonna zoom
in there
right it's somewhere here
takes a shilla they call it taxilla
the british call it taxila and now like
i said indians want to ape that and say
taxila it's not taxila it's takshashila
so it's in um
it's in northwest india or present day
by pakistan right so that's where it is
now what's the history this this is one
of the oldest known universes in the
entire world maybe the maybe the oldest
known university in the ancient world in
the entire world i mean it was a
it was a major university during the
time of the mauryan empire the great uh
the great uh statesman vaishnava
chanakya is known to have taught there
it's believed that he taught something
which would we would now call political
science yeah so he was a professor there
that's about two and a half thousand
years before today
so it was a very big university at that
time itself it may not have been a
university in the
present-day definition of university
with
semesters and professors and that
professors would be there but
it would have been
done differently in certain ways but it
was very much one of the oldest and
greatest seats of learning the world has
ever seen right so that is where taksha
shilla was in in in punjab now it's a
it's it's ruined and we know it's the
white horns who destroyed it typically
most of the great universities in india
we had lots of them dozens of them most
of them if not all of them were
destroyed by the invading turks in the
past one thousand years but in the case
of fukushila it is the invading shwetha
hunas
that destroyed it
most likely during the during the time
of mehirukula right so what is the deal
why did these people do this why did the
horns do this
as you if they had assimilated in indian
culture so we have to understand the
chronology of what happened so
uh
in the um
[Music]
when was this so it's in the fourth
fifth centuries etc
that these invasions happened first of
all the the hunik invasions happened
under
the first major king we know of was
called kingila
and this individual he carved out a
piece of territory for himself in north
west india presently afghanistan or that
region right
so that is in the
early fifth early to mid to late fifth
century this guy ruled in that region
between 430 and 490 a.d
right
so that is the first piece of territory
card out of india by the huns
now before
uh this guy you had many waves of
invasion so for instance during the
gupta period
when skanda gupta
was still a young man he was still a
teenager his father kumar gupta was the
emperor at that time the hunik raids the
invasions began in india
and skanda gupta proved his mettle as a
warrior as a leader of men as a leader
of armed forces in repelling these
invasions wave after wave of invasion
and afterwards eventually skanda gupta
became the emperor of india and he spent
his entire life repelling these hernik
invasions he spent his entire life
defending
india from the huns so this was between
450 and 470 or so a.d right this was the
time period and because of this
purely defensive maneuver which happened
over decades the treasury of the gupta
empire was kind of depleted and after
that the gupta empire underwent a kind
of decline right
so uh kingila
became king in a small region in
afghanistan far away from from the main
mainland present-day mainland of india
then you had a king called torah mana
i think he was the son of king if i'm
not mistaken so he was in power for
about 20 or so years 20 25 years the son
of thoramana was mehirakula
carved out a massive empire
in western india northern and western
india and he was in power for about 30
or so years roughly
now this guy mihir kula was a total
barbarian
he was an atheist the chinese pilgrim
song yoon came to india and he wrote a
travel logo whatever and he said this
guy mihir kula was a complete atheist he
was a barbarian
he committed all kinds of atrocities
against the buddhists and he also was
despised by the brahmanas
so he was despised by all indians he was
a brutal barbaric king he was an atheist
he believed in no god and he was a very
destructive and evil person cruel person
it is uh around this period around this
phase that the krishna was destroyed i'm
not sure who exactly destroyed it
whether it was
whatever
but it's around this time that it
happened most likely during the time of
mihirokula between 520 and 540 a.d right
so
so he was an atheist he despised all
kinds of religious displays and all i i
suppose he
perpetrated the various kinds of
atrocities against the brahmins against
the
against the buddhists at that time there
was a lot of buddhism in india
if you consider that to be a separate
religion technically historians do that
it's the same thing and once again i'm
going to get nice comments down there
don't care it's all right so that's what
happened
so it's around this time
that takes sheila was destroyed now like
i said maher kola was an atheist he did
not quite like indian culture afterwards
you had
other hunid kings like shri prabhavara
sena
from the mid five to my mid 500s to
about 590 a.d so this guy was very much
indianized
maybe he had an indian ancestor maybe
his mother or whatever yeah
and then you had other kings who
eventually assimilated within indian
society and who became great patrons of
indian culture for instance the great
scientist brahma gupta
who was born in 598 a.d he lived in
gurjardesh
right present-day bin mal
he lived under the patronage of a
supposedly honey king called vyagramukh
now this guy vagram was a great patron
of culture of science all that and he
was the patron of the great scientist
astronomer mathematician brahma gupta so
over time over the period of a century
or a century in the half the hons
they first fought india then they ruled
over india in a brutal manner and slowly
within after a certain amount of time
they became completely indianized and
they became great patrons of indian
culture of the indian sciences and all
that
so that's how it happened it did not
happen overnight
so initially they were destructive
initially they had cruel kings like
nihikou like maybe like kingula and so
on
but kingila is believed to have been the
guy
who constructed the buddhas in bamiyan
so that's that's also there so maybe it
was only mihirokula who was cruel and
and brutal
that's how it is now certain historians
today are trying to politicize this
matter and they are trying to portray it
as a hindu versus buddhist thing
these historians have political agendas
we know who they are i'm not naming them
today i have named them in the past
right
so they say if you i think if you look
at wikipedia for instance it will be
mentioned most likely that miricola was
a shaivite
a worshiper of rudra and he was
anti-anti-buddhist that's what they
mention i think in wikipedia if you look
it up that is not true that is a
complete outright lie and falsification
the chinese pilgrims who came to india
in search of wisdom and knowledge and
learning they all
are unanimous in their assessment of
mirkula that he was somebody who was
anti-all
religion and anti-culture he was
anti-brahmana anti-buddhist
anti-everything and the indian
he despised indian culture
even shwan zang who came a couple of
centuries later he also portrayed me
cola as a tyrant and a persecutor
of all indian religious and other
figures right
so that's how it is so these
uh
these narratives
that this was
hindu persecution of buddhism these are
lies
no such thing
okay so that's about this matter hope it
throws some light and clarity on this
and you can you can do some further
research if you can if you wish to
akash says why were the erstwhile german
empire and later nazi empire so eager to
to declare wars on their adjacent
countries why did they act in such an
aggressive manner
consecutively under 25 years and can we
hold them responsible for the world
wars
okay german empire and nazi germany so
we have to understand something in the
19th century until the mid 19th century
there was no such thing as germany you
had prussia which is i think northern
germany you had saxony and you had a
whole confederation loose confederation
of various german principalities
various german states
essentially independent kingdoms
that's what it was germany was never
united
the unification happened in 1871
and the architect of this uni
unification was a great uh
uh bismarck the german chancellor
bismarck he is the man who unified
germany he fought wars to unify germany
he fought the austro-hungarian empire he
fought the french he took some territory
from the french and under him the
entirety of germany was the for the
first time ever unified from the roman
times germany was
a hodgepodge of various tribes who
essentially had shared ethnicity and
language but were always at loggerheads
with each other
right
so it's always been that way so germany
was unified properly as a nation state
for the first time in 1871 at the end of
the franco-german war i believe and the
empire of germany was declared in 1871
in the palace of versailles in france
and
yeah so that's what happened
and after 1871 germany
embarked upon
a rapid and
very successful phase of reforms and
industrialization germany became a major
the major industrial power in europe it
leapfrogged all other european powers in
a very brief period of time full rapid
industrialization
reforms in society of more modern
society and so on and then there was a
buildup of of the navy
under the german kaiser wilhelm ii
at the turn of the century between the
18th and between the 19th and the 20th
centuries so as the german navy became
more powerful
this guy the kaiser williams william ii
he wanted a powerful navy and
quickly rapidly the german navy became
maybe the most powerful navy in the
world or maybe the second most powerful
navy in the world after the british
royal navy and that's what caused that's
what caused the tensions
now
there's a whole bunch of events that
happened in the early 20th century there
were
the ottoman empire was crumbling there
were there was conflict in the balkans
the austro-hungarians
annexed bosnia
they had designs on other parts of the
balkans the balkans declared
independence from the ottoman empire
lots and lots of things happened yeah
and then there was this incident in 1914
in june or june
when the heir to the throne of the
austro-hungarian empire france ferdinand
ii i believe his name was
he
went on a visit to sarajevo
uh in the balkans yeah and he was
assassinated there by gabrielle principe
who was a boston croat with serbian
background or something like that and
so the heir to the throne was
assassinated the austro-hungarians
declared war in a couple of months on
serbia serbia was allied to russia
and before declaring war on serbia the
austro-hungarians
spoke uh asked their allies in germany
should we go out with the war in germany
yeah yeah sure go ahead
so it was a big mess in europe
austria-hungary was allied
with the german empire and also allied
with the italians
the serbians were allied with russia the
russians were allied with the french
britain was in splendid isolation for
some time and the french in the italians
had a secret agreement of
of uh that they would not go to war
against each other
so when the austro-hungarians declared
war on serbia
the russians declared war on
austro-hungary because they were allies
of serbia
and that because the russians were
allies of france
austro-hungary also became the enemy of
france and because germany was the allah
of austria-hungary germany went to war
with france
and
russia and the whole
continent
of europe europe went to war
like it it was like
like a sudden explosion of ammunition
that's what happened so the war the
first world war we call it the first
world war this event in 1914 it was
triggered by
the austro-hungarian attempt to invade
serbia
and once this happened the germans went
to war again with the russians in the
french so it was started by the
austro-hungarians and then the russians
the germans obviously uh behaved in a
very aggressive manner they tried to go
for paris they took over luxembourg and
belgium belgium belgium gave them a lot
of resistance the moment the germans
invaded belgium the british got involved
because they had uh guaranteed the
neutrality of belgium and the reason why
the germans had to go through belgium
was because the german french border was
highly fortified and very well defended
by the french
so that's how the whole thing started
and it went on the ottomans got involved
winston churchill
tried to
invade
the dardanelles the gallipoli invasion
which was a complete disaster and so
much happened
at the end of the second of the first
world war in 1918 after the two russian
revolutions and so on
that then there was this this treaty was
signed the treaty of versailles i think
where the german empire had been
declared the same place
in this treaty
the germans were held solely responsible
for everything
and they were
made to pay very heavy reparations to
the other countries
so this was considered to be a national
humiliation and a very unfair treaty by
the german nation with some truth to it
i mean all the blame cannot be in
germany
of course the austro-hungarians are the
ones who started it but the
austro-hungarians suffered a complete
dismantling of their empire
the ottoman empire was also dismantled
and germany was made to pay very heavy
reparations and they were forced to sign
on the line
saying that they are solely responsible
for the war and this was in 1918 i
believe
and there was a 20-year period of no war
in europe but this treaty in versailles
was the root cause of world war ii
which again
in in the case of world war ii it is
because
hitler came to power because the people
were very deeply uh
upset
about the state of the economy and all
that and
they were they felt humiliated by the
treaty of versailles so hitler came to
power on a wave of nationalism
and he obviously was an evil person he
did horrific things but his overall
message to the people is that i will
restore german pride
and i will regain the territories that
germany was made to seed
in 1918 1919 1920 at that time so
germany was made to lose a lot of
territory at the end of world war one
poland was weakly recreated they lost
territory to the to belgium to france
and some other territories as well
you can look it up
so overall
world war ii started because the germans
felt deeply humiliated by the terms of
the treaty of versailles they were made
to pay incredible amounts of money in
reparations for a war that they were not
alone in starting
and so on
so that is the story of world war one
world war ii
of course hitler was very greedy he had
taken over the entirety of europe by
1941 and all that was left was the uk
and then he made a fatal miscalculation
instead of finishing off the uk
which was of course supported by the
americans instead of finishing of the uk
he turned eastwards
and he invaded the ussr with which he
had a non-aggression pact
and it was a very very very successful
invasion usually using the same
blitzkrieg tactics
they
captured massive amounts of russian
territory
within the first few months three
million russian soldiers had died i
always say this don't i that the
russians they start everything terribly
so that's what happened the russia the
germans made incredible rapid advances
into russia they had three different
directions in which they were going they
had this a2 line from an archangels to
uh atar khan
which they wanted to carry to capture
and they came
within
a stone's throw of moscow
but the russians just kept fighting they
kept dying but they came he kept coming
back they had about 14 to 15 million
reserve soldiers
well-trained
soldiers who had got gone back into
civilian life but who could be called
back at any time
that's what the russians had that's why
every country needs reserve soldiers
the lessons of history anyhow
big big story i can go on for for hours
about this but that's what happened
so uh
there's it's a very complex topic
the
war world war one was started by the
austro-hungarians not the germans but
the germans jumped on that on that
bandwagon
world war ii was started by germany to
avenge the incredible humiliation they
suffered in 1918 1919 the treaty of
versailles that's how it is
and they paid the price for that
asmita says here are my questions what
was the reason behind dividing germany
post world war two
why uh did the world war two impact uk
economically but not the us why many of
the defeated countries became vassal
states but not colonies of the us
why could the ussr not have such
subordinate states in europe so this is
a continuation of what i was saying at
the end of world war ii germany was
defeated
the russians the red army took berlin
the americans took part of western parts
of germany
that became the dividing line of the
cold war the iron curtain so berlin was
divided into two camps the eastern camp
and the western camp the western camp
was under the under the rule of the usa
and the eastern part of berlin was ruled
by the ussr
and the portions of germany which the
ussr had captured became east germany
the portions of the of germany which the
americans had captured
along with their various allied
minions
that became west germany at the end of
world war ii britain was spent it was a
spent force why did
the uk
become a spent force it's because they
have even in world war one they were
forced to rely on american supplies
food grains wheat
arms ammunition steel all of that in
world war one in order to fight back and
survive that world war one
so by the end of world war one the uk
was indebted to the americans even other
countries in europe were indebted to the
americans
in world war ii it went even worse the
uk was the only country that was holding
out to nazi germany and they were able
to hold out only because of this
constant stream of supplies from across
the atlantic from the u.s
to their country enormous amounts of
arms ammunition food all of that
without that the the uk would have would
have fallen to the nazis
and they took all of this they acquired
all of this on credit on loan from the
u.s
so at the end of world war ii the u.s
the uk was deeply in debt to the us the
us is a massive continent-sized country
free land which they have stolen from
the natives
enormo
an
inexhaustible supply of resources from
that land
there is so much farmland you can
produce enormous amounts of wheat there
are so many mines so many um
the industries can be built out of all
of that
so the u.s had an inexhaustible supply
of resources
and they were protected on one side but
the atlantic ocean and the other side
but the by the pacific pacific ocean so
it's a country that has no enemies they
have established complete hegemony in
north america and south america
and so nobody could touch the us
the european nations by the end of world
war ii were heavily indebted to the u.s
i believe the uk is still paying back
back
the debt of world war ii i nobody wants
to speak about this but i believe the uk
is even today in 2022 paying back the
debt to the us which they had acquired
in world war ii that's the situation
yeah so that's how it happened
so at the end of world war ii the uk was
a spent force it was no longer a great
nation
a top tier world power it became a
second class world power the only two
victors
in world war ii at the end of world war
ii were the ussr and the us and these
because the two superpowers
that's what happened
uh and western western europe was taken
over by the u.s the only major power
even today in western europe is the u.s
germany is under permanent u.s military
occupation it lays under permanent
military occupation today the uk is a
vassal state of the us and that's how it
happened it's a long complex story but
that is how it happened and the ussr
took over the entirety of eastern europe
the soviet bloc countries the warsaw
pact countries poland slovakia
yugoslavia hungary hungary to some
extent bulgaria these became us ussr's
satellite states
and so on so that's what happened so
it's not like the ussr did not have any
subordinate states or satellite states
they acquired a significant amount of
control over eastern europe
and i believe
the hungarians tried to
was it hungry i think it was hungary
they tried to rebel in
1956.
there were two rebellions i think there
was one in hungary and
and one in czechoslovakia you can look
up the exact details
uh and
soviet tanks rolled into the country
that's what happened i think one of
these things was in 1956.
so uh yeah
that's what happened
and that is the story in brief very
interesting uh period of history the
second world war which immediately gave
rise to the cold war
in which the entire world got involved
so in 1956 the the british
made one last attempt at regaining uh
a great power status they invaded suez
al suas which is the suez canal region
in egypt so what happened is that the
the
leader the ruler of egypt
he nationalized the sewage canal which
was
run by a british owned company i believe
so he nationalized it he acquired it and
he said that this this is our territory
it belongs to the people of egypt and we
should rule it we should control it
in retaliation the british and the
french invaded
this region's ways
port said and all that and they took it
over very rapidly
but the americans armed twisted the
british into
withdrawing
so the british withdrew the french
realized they could no longer trust the
british they also had to withdraw and
from there onwards there was a ussr
angle all this israel was involved it's
a long story
so it is in 1956 that it became official
that the uk is now a second class world
power it is firmly under the hill of the
us
and that's how it has been
so it's a very very detailed complex
long story i'm trying to make it as
short as possible but i would encourage
you all to study to read this to read
what actually happened in this period of
time very interesting period of history
very tumultuous
a period of history with lots of tragic
events and all but that's how human
history always is
eric says thank you for the content you
post very interesting thank you i had a
question about the us fighting the
british to gain independence how can
that tie into the theory that it there
was just a simple capital transfer
from london uk to washington dc i think
looking at the english-speaking
countries as one is not accurate you
also did mention that nehru chose to
align with the ussr instead of communis
because of communism
when the u.s had offered india the
military technological advances and so
on but because nehru was a british
appointee he chose the ussr how would
things have looked had india chosen to
align with the us okay
so this is something i i believe i am
the only person who has said this
that that after world war ii there was a
transfer of the headquarters of the
anglo-saxon empire from london uk to
washington dc i don't think anybody else
has said this
soon other geopolitical analysts and
strategists will start saying this
that's going to happen but thus far i am
the only person who has said this and i
understand why people don't uh believe
that or or find or are skeptical about
this claim but that's what really
happened and we have seen these things
happen these transfers of headquarters
from rome to constantinople it's
happened in the past now
it's true the us and the british had a
very antagonistic adversarial
relationship relationship for a very
long time from the u.s war of
independence what was the trigger the
cause for the u.s war of independence
because
the americans of that time of the 18th
century
were british they were british subjects
they served the british crown they paid
taxes to the british crown to the king
of england and the question they asked
themselves is why should we keep paying
taxes to a ruler who sits all the way
across the atlantic thousands of miles
away why should we pay taxes to him what
is he contributing to us what is it
doing for us why should we not take keep
all of this money for ourselves that we
are extracting out of the resources and
the territory of the us
so that's why they fought this war of
independence it was for financial
reasons for monetary reasons it was out
of greed
it was out of mutual greed the british
king the king of england
wanted
the taxes he was enjoying from the u.s
his quality in the us and the settlers
the british sectors in the us
asked themselves why should we keep
paying these taxes why should we not
keep all of this wealth for ourselves
that was the cause of the war
eventually the the americans
won the war they became independent of
the of the british of the english
that's what happened and even after that
there were lots of
conflicts
between the united states
and the in the british and the uk
which went on until the 20th century
yeah
and yet
eventually
the british came under the hill of the
u.s there is this very uh
you may have heard of what's called the
thucydides trap
when
you have an existing power with a
certain sphere of influence and a new
emerging power appears
and tries to take claim a piece of that
pie
conflict is inevitable and this is
something you see over and over and over
again
over thousands of periods thousands of
years of human history of world history
whenever an existing power feels
threatened by an emerging power in the
same sphere of influence conflict is
inevitable
yeah and yet there was no conflict ever
after the
the american war of independence between
the us and the british
because their interests aligned for a
long period of time of course the
british still were a major power they
still had their so-called british empire
until
that the the the world war ii era and
then the americans took over the whole
thing because the british became deeply
deeply indebted to the americans and the
americans had
the military firepower to subdue the
british anytime they wanted if they
stopped repaying the debt
so at the root of everything
is hard power
the british navy
they lost a significant portion of their
navy in 1947.
the british indian navy became the
indian navy
right it controlled the entire indian
ocean region
from
malacca to to hormuz to to babal mandib
singapore all of that
they lost that they lost eventually the
control of suez so their empire crumbled
essentially within a decade or so
and the americans took over the reigns
of everything so that is what happened
if you
no historian says it in these words
that the british empire continued in the
form of the american empire but that's
essentially what happened you have to
look at all the supply chains what are
empires built on they are built on
military power on economic power
economic power is it all depends on
infrastructure supply chains railroads
trade roads all those things so if you
look at what happened nothing
disappeared
all the infrastructure of the british
empire remained intact
after the 1940s but it was all taken
over and
built upon enhanced by the americans
so that's what happened now when it
comes to nehru he was an anglophile but
he was a fabian socialist and that's why
he was deeply
uh in awe of the
the kind of industrialization the ussr
had achieved in a very short period of
time he wanted to replicate that in
india but in a fabian socialist manner
which means at a very slow rate very
slow pace of improvement one percent two
percent three percent growth per year
that is called the nehru and rate of
growth that's why he aligned himself
with the ussr instead of the us despite
the u.s offering india
nuclear technology and a seat on the
permanent seat on the u.n security
council
so that's what happened had
so because nehru was there this was
never possible had somebody else been
there hypothetically if subash bose was
in power he may have
chosen to align with the us
and then that would have been
a difficult dance to play because the
americans wanted a new wasal state a
major country like the like india to
become part of their uh geopolitical
grouping
so there was there's always the danger
that when you align yourself
with the interests of a bigger larger
more powerful country you become a
satellite state india became a satellite
state of the ussr until 1991 when the
ussr broke up
india was
a de facto
russian satellite state
so
had india aligned with the us the in
india could possibly have become a u.s
satellite state it's it's possible and
it's entirely possible but what was
better
on balance
the kind of the the kind of decay
and corruption india witnessed from the
1950s to to recent to until very
recently or a more
rapid rate of growth the kind of growth
japan so for instance when a country in
1947 india
india amounted for less than two percent
of the world's gdp
india had a population of 300 plus
million individuals
the life expectancy in 1947 was about
i don't know 28 30 32
thereabouts that's how that's how
that's how badly india was destroyed
for a country in that situation
it is not
unreasonable to expect 10
economic growth year upon year for the
next two three decades india could have
grown very rapidly the way japan emerged
from the ruins but because of nehru's
decision we stayed
india stayed remain in poverty and and
uh
destitution for a very long time for
decades in the case and decades so
things could have been different yeah of
course india could the americans would
have wanted to extract the pound of
flesh from india but
if you have the right leadership you can
play
you can dance in a certain manner with
the with the
bigger power and it could benefit your
country in a variety of ways so that's
how it is it's all hypothetical because
it's about what if this happened or what
if that happened well here we are so
that's that's what it is
okay lakshay says i've noticed that you
know in our country many people listen
to english music just to appear cool
despite not even fully understanding the
lyrics what do you think about this what
kind of music do you listen to
uh like i said when you have a dominant
culture in the world the anglo-saxon
culture it is all powerful it is all
pervasive
so people want to copy and ape that and
their culture and their their cultural
manifestations like music and all that
in order to appear cool even if they
even if they don't really understand it
right
don't they don't understand the lyrics
or whatever they just want to copy that
and appear cool because if you if you
sound american if you if you pretend to
be western you look more cool than your
desi counterparts so that's how it is
so that's unfortunate but that's just
how society and sociology and psychology
works
so i think it's unfortunate
what kind of music do i listen to i
listen to music from all over the world
uh
i'm a big fan of mongolian music
yeah for instance mongolian folk music
from mongolian folk rock rock
you may have heard perhaps of a
mongolian rock band called the who which
is a fork rock band it is rooted in
mongolian traditional music and i'm also
into
pure proper mongolian folk like zorik
vancig who's who who has this famous
song called chinggis khani magdal which
has a variety of interpretations and
versions i'm a fan of of uh
romani music from europe gypsy jazz
uh artists like bireli lagren and django
reinhardt
winterstein
gypsy jazz romani the romanian indian
origin people in europe and flamenco
flamenco is a romani art form from spain
flamenco music is incredibly beautiful i
am
i like
music from western africa mali the roots
of the blues artists like uh
tumani diabate
ali fakature what's her name
i forget her name fatima
yawara and so on
japanese music chinese music i like
music from all over the world but the
most interesting
form of music for me is indian classical
music
it is the oldest form of music we know
of in the world it's the most advanced
form of music in the world
and we are losing that
it's incredibly
rich complex and beautiful
you know
we have the concept
in indian classical music the
the central concept is the concept of
the raag
a raag is not just a musical scale it's
much more than that every log has a
certain scale maybe an ascending scale
that is different from a descending
scale you have
sonant notes and consonant notes and
drone notes and so much more it's
complex it's beautiful
with a certain with a rock you can
create a certain atmosphere and a
character and a personality every rag is
different
uh there are certain drugs that are for
the morning time some rugs for evening
time some rags evolve evoke certain
seasons
and so on
it's a very complex thing and and i wish
that people would explore that more
so uh
unfortunately indian classical music is
dying out today
that's where we are and that's very
unfortunate uh i wish that people would
explore that more but it's not cool
nowadays you know that's where we are
so i think that people should explore
indian music more but the question is
where do you explore that
which are the great artists all the
great artists are from the past people
like nikhil banerjee and pandit ravi
shankar and hari prasad jawasya
all of these people
are have passed on unfortunately so
there are no great artists alive today
that i can think of maybe a couple
but all the great artists are in the
past and there is no innovation
happening in indian classical music it's
all with the same old instruments
i would like to see people innovate
and use modern instruments and
electronics and all that to play indian
ragas and all that that would be
fascinating there was this artist called
charanjit singh from the 1980s
who played
who who came up with an album called 10
ragas to a disco beat
it was indian ragas on
roland or some synthesizers incredible
sounds very modern sounds futuristic and
sounds rooted in indian culture it's
amazing
so i would encourage all of you to
explore indian classical music would you
like to
why don't why don't i demonstrate a
little bit yeah
let me demonstrate just so that you get
an idea of how it is
so this thing is called a guitar it's my
it's my old guitar 20 years old so for
example i spoke about ragas and ragas
are all about
seasons so listen to this this is called
[Music]
so this is called ragavasanth it it
evokes the springtime
there is something called raga bhairav
which is a
it's a very early morning dawn or for
instance it's like this the scale goes
like this
so this is the raga basanta there is
something called raga shivaranjani for
instance it sounds somewhat like this
the scale is like this
one second where is it
here we are
[Music]
this is a raga shivaranjani you may have
heard certain hindi songs based on this
for instance
[Music]
so bollywood has been
using indian ragas
bollywood and various other forms of
various other
music industries have been using ragas
but they don't they don't
quite publicize the fact all indian
music is based on
the system of ragas that comes in from
from olden times
it's the oldest music system in the
world
so i would encourage you all to try and
look it up try and uh partake of that
this cultural richness that we have
okay gotham says is it true that brahmi
and karoshi script are derived from
aramaic as they say in wikipedia that is
a complete fabrication as always as
always
our historians and linguists and foreign
historians and linguists will claim that
everything that exists in india came
from somewhere else now aramaic is a
semitic or proto-semitic or some
something like that that sort of
language and script
and they claim it came from there so
let's see what wikipedia has to say let
me take a look
wikipedia brahmin
let me share my screen where is
wikipedia brahmi script
okay what does it say about the brahmi
script
so if we look here if you look at the
so-called parent systems it says that
brahmi is derived from aramaic which is
derived from phoenician which is derived
from the protocyanic script utter
nonsense and of course they're they're
requesting us to pay money
and support wikipedia sorry don't ever
pay money to wikipedia all right please
don't do that
right
so this is what wikipedia says it says
that the brahmi script is derived from
the aramaic alphabet
which is derived from the phoenician
alphabet which is derived from the
proto-sinaitic script
let's see what the what it says about
karoshi
it says karoshi comes from aramaic once
again which comes from phoenician from
proto-scientific from egyptian
hieroglyphics which means they are
claiming that all of indian culture all
the indian writing systems everything
comes from abroad there's nothing
indigenous about india
absolute lies
and that's my guitar falling over that's
okay
so that's the lie that's been
perpetrated for for for
like a couple of centuries
and that's not true the brahmi script is
most likely derived
out of
the
saraswati script
so we have still not been able to
decipher this saraswati hindu script we
have lots of inscriptions
and uh
some attempts have been done some
individuals like irawat and mahadevan
came up with some ridiculous fake desire
decipherments he said it is prototamil
i have gone through the manuscript the
pdf which is available online in which
he makes the claims he does not provide
any justification or basis for these
claims
for the claims that this is prototyping
he says this so and so uh symbol stands
for so-and-so tamil word on what basis
do you come up with these claims there
has to be some some logical basis
there's no logical basis
so people have tried to decipher
ever have claimed to have deciphered the
saraswati sindh script but thus far it's
not been proven recently some more
innovations have happened um
which need to be looked into
i think it would not be very difficult
to decipher this script as long as you
are doing it full time and and seriously
and in a scientific manner but what i
can say for sure is that the brahmi and
karoshi scripts are not derived from any
non-indian scripts or alphabet alphabets
brahmi is very i think there is this
article by uh dr subash
in which he has shown that a certain
brahmi um
certain indus valley saraswati
script
inscription
actually has uh can be deciphered and
it it represents a sanskrit phrase or
something like that
so uh
it's something that needs to be put to
rest properly and it it will happen
surely
soon
so i i don't agree with this this
ridiculous this patently false
fabricated claim
that brahmi and karoshi are derived from
arabic complete fabrication complete
liars
okay vampy says i have always wondered
how newton and leibniz both derived
equations
of differential calculus at the same
time
a concept can be devised by a number of
people but from history we get that only
one at a time gets the equations right
while they both contributed to the field
of mathematics
does the situation mean
that they both learned the equations
from another source and made it their
own listen it's ridiculous
that two guys one in the island of
england one on the island of england and
one in germany came up with the same
exact same
discovery
of differential calculus which nobody
had ever done before in europe
in the same year at the same time it's
ridiculous what really happened is that
calculus was discovered in in india
it is known to have been discovered
india at least a century before these
two individuals existed
and most likely it dates back to way
before that so
the earliest known evidence of calculus
of infinite series of differential
calculus and so on comes from the kerala
school of mathematics
a century
more than a century before newton and
leibniz claimed to have made this
discovery and at the time we had these
so-called what are they called jesuit
priests
who were
going around india
and
trying to
acquire
various forms of indian knowledge and
wisdom
so the jesuit priests are the scientists
of the vatican
they are priests
they are employed by the vatican but
they go they go around the world
trying to acquire scientific knowledge
and they will bring it back to the west
and then it would be used in a variety
of forms
so all of the for instance you have the
kepler's law of planetary emotions the
three cap kepler's three laws of
planetary motion
these three laws
he was able to come up with these three
laws based on an enormous amount of
astronomical data
that astronomical data came from india
it was indian astronomical data that he
examined and studied for a number of
years and on that on the basis of that
he was able to come up with the kepler's
laws of planetary motion the three laws
excuse me
similarly these two guys
newton and leibniz i'm not saying that
we're not good scientists newton was one
of the greats
and he said
that if he has made any any great
progress in science it's because he
stood on the shoulders of giants
he has made this statement he has said
this look it up standing on the
shoulders of giants
newton said that but he did not identify
the giants on whose shoulders he stood
so it's clear that all of this knowledge
came from india it's becoming more and
more clear with every passing year with
more information coming out with all of
this knowledge
this indian scientific knowledge whether
it is algebra whether it's trigonometry
whether it's calculus infinite series
whatever
all of that came out of india
made its way first into the arabic world
and sometimes straight
into europe like in the case of of
calculus so that's what happened all of
this all of these are indian inventions
western science has progressed in leaps
and bounds and today it's the most
advanced
science and technology in the world it
is all based on a foundation of indian
science
from the
uh middle ages onwards that's when the
europeans first came into contact with
indian
scientific literature and that's what
they absorbed
incorporated into their own their own
academic system i would say and improved
upon that slowly that's what happened
okay eddie says i only recently started
learning more about indian history and
current day politics
one question popped into my mind how is
the writer ready kipling viewed in india
today
uh him being english and all that
that's a that's a good question so uh
rudyard kipling is an interesting
individual he was born in india i think
in
what was then called bombay now mumbai i
think he was born in bombay
or somewhere in india
and uh
he was deeply influenced by india he
wrote a lot about india the story of
rikitikitavi the mongoose
the jungle book mowgli
shirkhan balu bhagira and so on and he
wrote a number of poems some very racist
poems for instance
and some not so racist poems so for
instance when he writes his very famous
poem called the white man's burden
is a deeply racist poem it's about the
white man carrying the uncivilized
barbaric backward primitive natives on
their back
it it implies that all progress in the
world depends on the white man
let me show you a caricature that was
based on
rudyard kipling's poem the white man's
burden
there it is it shows the us
and the uk carrying all the
primitive backward native
races of the world on their shoulders
so you have these rocks called barbarism
oppression ignorance superstition
brutality vice
cannibalism ignorance slavery cruelty
and at the at the top you have
civilization which is represented by the
british and the americans
the americans are carrying the cubans
the africans the native native americans
and so on the british are carrying the
indians and the chinese towards
civilization
this is rudyard kipling's white man's
burden which is deeply offensive and
deeply racist to the non-white peoples
he also came up with this poem called
gangadeen
which is kind of not so
prejudiced against indians so this is a
scene from a movie made made about the
poem based on the poem
so that's how it is so how do people in
india view radiate coupling today most
indians still worship him
radiate kipling is an integral part of
any uh english literature
course
at the
bachelor's level or master's level
and he is portrayed as was one of the
greatest english boys which he probably
was he was a great poet and great writer
but he was deeply racist and that is
typically not known to most indians
yeah
so even today india is a deeply
colonized nation the attitudes are still
deeply colonized and most indians think
that the british did us a great favor
by colonizing us and uplifting us from
our ignorance
and because of that most indians still
think that kipling is a great great
person
and they don't know about his racism and
his attitudes towards indians so that is
where we are vis-a-vis
kipling
who was alan octavian hume
and what was the actual purpose behind
the making of the indian national
congress so this individual alan
octavian hume he was a british
administrator who
spent his entire career i think in india
and let's let's google this guy
alan
octavian
hume and let me
put that on the screen once again
as always
wikipedia is not a reliable source of
information it is highly biased
but
for the sake of
convenience i'm just showing you the
wikipedia article okay
please remember that
so this is uh the article about alan
hume
so this individual
uh spent most of his life
most of his working life in india
he was a british civil servant political
reformer ornithologist and botanist
and the founder of the indian national
congress he founded the indian national
congress in 1885. now let's go back to
his career so he was he was in india
when the first war of independence
happened in 1857
he was the commissioner of customs from
1867 to 1870
and he was the mastermind behind
building
the 2 500 mile long inland customs line
inland customs line
this is what it looked like
if it will load this is it
from
northern india all the way into eastern
india this was the great indian customs
line also known as the great indian
hedge
all right
so this was built in order to prevent
the uh
the transportation of salt
from india's coastal regions eastwards
because the british had imposed a
massive
punitive salt tax
and they wanted all indians to pay the
tax before they acquired salt so this
hedge was built to prevent
the transportation of salt from the
coastal regions in the west
to the eastern and northern regions of
india
and because i mean
and and this uh the english writer roy
marxum has written a book about this now
i i'm not sure how many what was the
see there is something called salt
deprivation if you differ if you deprive
a human being or any animal also of salt
eventually you will go into this salt
deprivation mode which will eventually
lead to death
it is estimated that several million
indians died as a consequence of the
building of this
great indian hedge because they were no
longer able to acquire salt you need
salt in the diet in some quantities if
you are deprived of salt you're gonna
you're gonna eventually die
so most likely several million indians
died as a consequence of this policy of
this action
done by alan octavian hume and
eventually this individual
founded the indian national congress in
1885. the purpose of the indian national
congress was to shepherd the
indian independence movement
into a non-violent
harmless direction
so they wanted indians to feel that
there is a proper independence movement
happening
but they wanted that movement
to be completely non-violent and
completely harmless to the british
and once that was established they could
portray any violent resistance to the
british as terrorism
so that was the true purpose of the end
of the creation of the indian national
congress and all the subsequent leaders
of the indian national congress were all
british educated indians who were
anglophiles and who could speak british
who could speak english very well
you can name who they are i know
i'm sure you know who those great indian
leaders are
so that was the purpose of creating the
indian national congress
okay mango elaichi says what are your
views on dr s j shankar's statement
on the u.s supporting pakistan and
ambassador t.s tirimothy's statement
in the united nations about
religiophobia very important statements
so uh i have been saying this for quite
some time for a long time for the
longest time that the us
has for the longest time since the 1980s
supported and financed and funded
pakistani terrorism in india
it's well known
but no indian leader or diplomat has
ever said this until now
i mean explicitly clearly so i think
doctors have said this in a certain
manner in
in diplomatically appropriate language
that the conflict between india and
pakistan is essentially a creation of
the u.s something to that effect i don't
remember the exact quote you can look it
up i'm saying it in my own words
so that's what dr s j shunger said and
that is absolutely 100 correct
these
assertions need to be made
because the british tried to the the
americans not the british same thing
the americans tried to lecture india
about human rights
about uh
the way india should conduct conduct its
foreign affairs or india's relations
with pakistan and other countries
and so and a whole host of other topics
so these statements need to be made to
show them the mirror that you are the
creators
of many of these conflicts and you are
no great paragons of virtue when it
comes to
human rights and the so-called
rules-based world order they are the
biggest violators of human rights and
the rule in the so-called rules-based
world order so dr jashankar's statement
is very important secondly our
ambassador to the un
ambassador thiru murthy said something
about religiophobia
the the thing in the west is that
they talk about the phobia a phobia of a
certain religion a certain religious
phobia but they don't
accept
that there are
antipathic tendencies towards other
religious as well
typically when somebody speaks about
hindu phobia which is a real thing
the west says there is no such thing and
especially it will be indian internal
interlocutors in the west will say there
is no such thing as endophobia so there
are lots of indians who live in the west
people of indian origin who have taken
up citizenship in the west
and they are employed
as the spokespeople of the west when it
comes to india so that it appears like
it is indians who are saying that you
indians are are killing lies
so typically it will be people in
academia it will be professors to be
historians and political officials of
indian origins you know low level or
medium ranking people and they will come
out and say no there is no such thing as
in hindu phobia there are plenty of
indian origin academics in the west
who are the biggest
enemies of india you can see them all
all over twitter and in various
publications
about foreign affairs etc so they are
the ones who typically say that there is
no hindu phobia hindu phobia is a real
thing it's existed for for the longest
time in the us in the west and
even in india today
india is probably the most hindu foreign
nation in the world
look at the government policies i'm not
saying the central government i'm saying
look at certain state government not all
state governments but overall the
constitution
reduces in hindus to second second-class
citizens to the status of second-class
citizens hindus are not allowed to
administer their own temples there is
clear hindu phobia and various
government policies in certain states
are clearly hindu phobic
so that's about india's internal hindu
phobia but when it comes to the west the
west has a very old history of being
hindu phobic in india's
institutional hindu phobia has its roots
in the british occupation of india which
was hindu phobic they tried to destroy
hinduism right
so
ambassador
tiramoti made a statement about
religiophobia
that we have to recognize religiophobia
that every religion to some extent some
more some less
are targeted in this manner and there
are antipathic tendencies to towards
against all religions especially
hinduism so you cannot say that only one
or two religions have phobias and others
don't
that is just not right
so these are both very important
statements and this needs to be repeated
kostub says recently russia replaced
saudi arabia as
to become the second largest oil supply
to india we are reducing oil dependency
on the middle east is it a good move
will the u.s again use the middle east
to provoke india like they did in the
last few weeks
for importing more russian gas and oil
the us will use all resources at its
disposal
to provoke india
and to pressurize india
even if india accedes to all the demands
they will still keep on doing that
that's how it's going to be
so i think it's a good thing that india
is diversified diversifying its supply
of oil and
energy energy security is very important
and you cannot depend on a single region
or a single nation for your energy
security you need to procure your oil
your gas
coal whatever it is
from a variety of sources you need to
diversify your portfolio you need to
have a wide diverse bouquet
of energy sources we should pro procure
oil from the russians from the saudis
from the kuwaitis from the iranians why
not
from the umanis
from the nigerians from the venezuelans
from the russians from from uh
from the americans if required
we should diversify our sources and
that's always something that's good for
you because then you are no longer you
are not going to be dependent on one
source and nobody can blackmail you as a
consequence of that so we still
procure a significant amount of oil from
the from the gulf region from the
southeast and from the countries in this
region we have excellent relations with
these countries
right so i think it's a very good thing
it's a very good move
and
nobody should feel
uh
should feel aggrieved about india's
policy decisions we are an independent
nation we have an independent internal
and external policy and we will do what
is best for ourselves and as long as our
mutual interests align with other
countries we will work with all of them
that's called multi-alignment it's
called multi-polarity and that's the
kind of
world we seek which is based on mutual
interest and mutual respect so that's
what we are doing and it's a very good
policy move
right let's take a few more questions
swapnil
says okay
what okay
what form were the human species during
the chichalub event
that wiped out the dinosaurs from the
earth
so let's understand the chronology
the chichalub impact event
happened roughly 66 million years before
today
66 million 6.6 crore years before today
all right
at that time there were no human beings
the human species homo sapiens is about
300 000 years old
the entirety of humanity is about
roughly 2 million years old before that
you had pre-human species
about three million years before today
the ancestors of us
and the ancestors of the chimpanzees
were the same the two branches were
united
just three million years before today
so three million years before today
there were no humans there were
pre-humans
the czech impact event happened 66
million years ago
so clearly there would be no human
species around at that time our
ancestors did
exist at the time
mammals
they were about this size
they were rat like mammals
they survived this horrific cataclysm
they survived it most dinosaurs died out
but our ancestors survived it but they
were not humans at the time they were
rat like creatures mammals who lived
mostly underground
like
rats
yeah
and when this
impact event happened let me show you
where it happened we should look at the
map always
um excuse me
let's go back to the map so where did
this event
happen
i'm gonna
go so this impact event happened in the
yucatan peninsula
in mexico
this here is yucatan
yukatan province of mexico you go
further to the west you will come up
there is this town called chikshulub
here it is it's a small village called
czech it is roughly the epicenter of the
impact event
half of the crater the crater is now
buried underground because it's been a
very long time half of it is in the
ocean
and half of it is on land so that's
where this impact happened when this
impact happened india was not part of
eurasia india was in the middle of the
of the indian ocean the indian
subcontinent had woken up from africa
about 100 million years before today it
was in the process of moving towards
eurasia so india at the time was
somewhere around this region
and it was a time of intense volcanism
and that left behind the badlands of
central india the deccan traps okay so
that's what happened in reef
there were no humans at the time
our ancestors did exist but they existed
in the form of rat like creatures
all right
right
let's take some other questions
armand says the author of mujmal tawarik
has quoted an extinct sanskrit work
according to which the original
inhabitants of sindh where the judges
and the medes
the above was mentioned in an article
about jets in the
on a punjabi defense on the pakistani
defense website
is it true that the jets and the meds
were the original inhabitants of synth
it all depends on the times time frame
that you're looking at
if you look at the last hundred years
you had a certain
ethnicity that lived in the so-called
sydney people if you look at the last
1000 years maybe juts
lived there if you look at the last 2000
years maybe the medes lived there the
medes were in eastern where a northern
iranian ethnicity
you go back five thousand years
these inhabitants of this region which
is now called sindh where the people of
the saraswati and civilization the
ancestors of most indians today
so it depends
on the lens with which you look you look
at the moment with your naked eyes with
your bare eyes you will see a certain
image of the moon you take binoculars
and look at the moon you will see more
detail about the moon you take a high
powered telescope you will see actual
rocks and stones and pebbles on the
surface of the moon it depends
on what
magnification you use and what lens you
look at the moon with similarly if you
look at sindh or rajasthan or gandhar
and you want to know the original
inhabitants you have to look at you have
to ask yourself what time scale are you
referring to
if you want to talk about gandhar
and if you want to look at the past 500
years
you one would have to say that the
pashtuns
are the inhabitants of gandhara
if you look at the past two thousand
years
the ancestors of the pashtun the rajputs
and their ancestors were the original
inhabitants of gandhar you go back 5000
years you had the mahabharat era
possibly of the time the the vedic or or
post vedic indians of that time who were
the inhabitants of gandhar and so on and
so forth
so
nobody sprang out of the soil
human history is a history of migration
uh the best theory that we have as of
today is that is the out of africa
theory which says that about 70 or so
thousand years before today the out of
africa migration
of homo sapiens happened and then we
colonized eventually the whole
surface of the planet and india was the
foundational zone the original founders
zone of the out of africa migration
so that's how it is so
i would say that the original
inhabitants of sindh
for all intents and purposes were the
people of the saraswati hindu
phase
of india's civilization that goes back
about six or so
about 10 000 years before today right
i think the oldest evidence
of this phase of our civilization is
from virana in haryana but you have
other very ancient sites in sindh and in
present-day balochistan as well
so one can say with a very high degree
of confidence and certainty that the
original inhabitants of this region are
the people of the saraswati sindhu phase
of our indian civilization and that's
the answer
hopefully it makes sense
right
um
suraj says is there any correlation
between power and influence of the same
are they the same
do influential people have any real
power or can power exist without any
influence by influence i mean popularity
among the masses let's say i have a
person
i've answered this in the past but let's
let's take it again
let's say i have a person who is very
popular on social media this individual
let's say it's a he let's say it's a
hero okay this guy
has 10 million followers
across three four different social media
platforms twitter instagram youtube
facebook whatever total 10 million
so what does it mean to be influential
it means that when this person has
something to say
then people will listen
and they will consider it seriously
that's called influence some may agree
some may disagree but they will all
listen to him because he seems to be
because they see they find him
interesting and they find him somebody
they should listen to so that's called
influence people will listen to you and
they will take you seriously and they
may agree or disagree
that's influence now let's take a person
too a second person
he doesn't have
10 million followers on social media but
he has 10 million trained soldiers
heavily armed soldiers at his disposal
who will obey him without question
that is power
whatever he says they will immediately
implement it
no questions asked
absolute obedience that is power
influence does not
mean that there is absolute obedience
so influence is not power power means
you have influence but influence does
not mean you have power that is the
difference
um
whoa
is it okay to kill ants for fun
please don't
please don't do that
it's not okay
what's the fun
i don't get it please don't do it
uh what was your reaction when you first
got to know the true history of india
i know it wasn't because of a few books
it took a lot of research which
eventually led you to knowing the true
history
but still how was the reaction during
the process would love you to repeat the
reaction oh my god that was a reaction
you know it doesn't happen overnight
initially like everybody else i believed
whatever the textbooks told us
then out of curiosity i started looking
at various other things i think uh
as a kid
as a seven-year-old 10 year old kid i
used to read history books but i was
never interested in indian history
because it was so depressing
so i knew about world history from a
very young age it's only in my 20s that
i started becoming interested about
indian history in indian history
and i started looking up research papers
about archaeology about genetics etc and
that's when i started uncovering
certain truths which are which i had not
known until then it was a slow gradual
process but
very quickly
i started realizing that everything we
have been told is a lie much of it is a
lie and even the truth is distorted
so there was no
eureka moment
it was a slow gradual process
until 2017 i used to even believe in the
aryan invasion theory 2016 or 2017
then one day for whatever reason i i
told myself let me take a look at the
actual
um
actual evidence
you know the primary sources not what
textbooks tell you not what the
writers tell you but the primary
evidence the actual research
so i went into archaeology i went into
history
sorry genetics i went deep into
linguistics and then what stared me in
the face was complete shock
and that's when i wrote the first
article about the rn invasion myth i
think it was in 2017
in which i put all of the the the data
across multiple
disciplines together
so
yeah it's it's a slow gradual process
and there was no
sudden moment of realization when then
when i realized everything is wrong it
was a slow process
okay let's take
one more arpan says i'm astonished
seeing you explaining physics with deep
knowledge from first principles itself
you explain straight reflecting your
depth of research i'm
sure you have other areas of interests
too how do you cope with such switch of
paradigms
being in this context what do you think
about the pro about proverbs like a
person who chases two rabbits rabbits
ends up catching neither or jack of all
trades and master of none
well i don't know about proverbs i'm
sure that
they are they have some some wisdom to
them
see the thing about history is that once
you study history
let's say as a hobby
once you
acquire the knowledge it stays with you
at least for me it's like that i've been
studying history from a very young age
out of curiosity as a hobby not as a
primary pursuit so in my free time time
i would read history books and all that
i i found it very interesting and for
whatever reason i find that i'm able to
absorb whatever i find interesting and i
retain the knowledge so it's a long
process and that's always been a hobby
until recently
my primary
area of computation
competence is science it's physics
physics theoretical physics in the case
of physics it's like athletics
you take a break
then you are no longer good at it it's
something you have to keep on
it's a process you have to keep keep
continuing continue doing
so scientific research if you take a
break from it for one year or two years
when you return to it you find that you
are no longer that competent it will
take you
a few months to again reach that level
of competence so in the case of science
you have to continuously practice it
it's like being an athlete you you take
a break from for a few months you lose
your mojo so to say
in the case of history it's not like
that
so my i am very clear about the fact
that my primary area of expertise my
primary area of competence is
theoretical physics it's science
that's what i truly am that's what i
enjoy the most talking about but over
the decades i've acquired a lot of a
great amount of understanding
at my level about history and because i
understand history i also understand
geopolitics so i speak about that
right so i don't find that i need to
keep practicing the reading of history
every single day in order to be good at
history it's something that accumulates
over time but in the case of science you
have to stay on top of your game
so it's two different things totally
different the the pursuit of
expertise or competing in history is a
very different game
from being a top class scientist or a
world class scientist very different
mindset very different approach
so it's not that you that you're chasing
two rabbits it's got it's like you have
one rabbit in one hand and you're going
after another rabbit you've already
caught one rabbit and you're going after
another rabbit and i have lots of other
interest i am i am very deeply i used to
be very deeply interested in music
but i i no longer do that i haven't
played the guitar in years now
but uh it's something that i was really
fascinated with and music is something
that's fascinating because it's purely
mathematical and it it also has
implications about human consciousness
and all that why do we enjoy certain
sounds and dislike certain other kinds
of sounds why why are certain
frequencies pleasing to us and not
others and so on so uh that's something
i was always also fascinated with about
but i no longer have the time to pursue
my interest in music as a practitioner
as a performing musician
as somebody who plays music
so i nowadays only listen to music so
you can't chase all the rabbits in the
world you have to make a choice of which
rabbits you want to chase so i have one
rabbit in my hand which is history and
geopolitics i don't need to keep
practicing it
in order to retain that knowledge it's
there it's not going to go anywhere
but physics science is something you
need to stay on top of the game
so i have one rabbit in the hand and i'm
chasing another i'm not chasing two
different rabbits going in two different
directions if i were to also try and
pursue music
in a serious manner then i would have
one rabbit in my hand and i would be
chasing two different rabbits that's not
very advisable so that's how i see it
yeah
okay let's take a couple of questions
from the live chat
if you have questions
uh fire away
all right is there any question
um
what's your view on the vedic age how
many people used to live in that era is
there any place that still exists now
the vedic age was i don't know how many
thousands of years ago the rig vedic age
would be around the time when the
saraswati was still a big thing
the great saraswati river was still a
river in its prime which is about 6000
bc
so i would say the vedic age somewhere
around that time period
and it's obviously the the population of
our ancestors was must have been much
lower than what it is now
uh
this
the vedic age was primarily centered
around the saraswati
valleys
which is western and northern india
today
present day haryana punjab sindh the
western region and i'm sure the
population was much less than what it is
today because the vedic people were
grouped into various clans a clan is
like an extended family so that's how it
was do this do those places exist today
of course they exist today the same
places exist today which they existed
earlier
so that's what i think about it
that's what i feel about it
so basically you're a physics batsman
who bowls us through a bit no i am
an all-rounder i am primarily a physics
batsman but i'm also a very good
history bowler i don't his bold history
a bit i do not see myself as a an
amateur historian or somebody who
doubles in history i think i have a
reasonable amount of competence i am
saying this without any arrogance or
something it's just a self assessment
i know how much time i've put into
studying history as well which is more
than most people would would put it in
any one field so
so i
it's not quite quite accurate but yeah
um
okay this is an interesting question
india has decided to to host a g20
meeting in jammu and kashmir what are
your thoughts i think it's a very good
move
why not
why not it also sends a very
good and strong message to the world
okay what else do we have what else do
we have
um
let us see
from where did you learn how to play
ragas can you tell ah
i'm a self-taught guitar player
i taught myself how to play the guitar
no one taught me that and then you can
look up the raga notation online
if you want to know the the notes of a
raga let's say you want to
learn the notes of raga
make malar for instance you can google
it and they will tell you what are the
main what is the main scale the
ascending scale the descending scale
which notes are to be played which is
the
dominant note which is a subdominant
note what are the drone notes and then
you can look up various google i mean
various youtube videos about how it
sounds and you can try and imitate that
i am not
a professional musician i am an amateur
complete amateur in that but it's
something i find very fascinating and i
tried whenever i have some time i dabble
in that trying to play ragas on the
guitar
so i'm entirely self-taught in that
all right i think we're done here it's
oh yeah it's it's gone beyond two hours
so thank you everybody for the for your
questions always
interesting questions keep it going
we'll do it again next week
i will see you in the next episode and
those of you who have the jee i came to
know that the joint entrance exam of the
iit is on so those of you who are
appearing for the je i wish you all the
best go win go do well
and
yeah that's it i will see you in the
next episode take care bye bye all the
best